All
right, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Oops, so today this
fell, so not letting me record. Okay, so
today's
דף daf is ט"ו, Yud-Vav, fifteen, and we pick up with יד
עמוד ב. yud dalet amud bet. They were in the middle of
a whole discussion about הולך כזכי. holech k'zachi. So there are two
important points I wanted to clarify from last time. Number one is
we went through a whole discussion where a guy gives a שטר
שחרור shtar shichrur or he's and he's saying like הולך holech to
my you know bring this to the גט get to the to
the other person or he's paying back a debt and he says
you know bring this to the bring this money to the guy
I owe the money to to the guy I have the פקדון
pikadon to and there the גמרא Gemara assumes that הולך holech is
כזכי k'zachi and the question by the case of paying off the
debt or the פקדון pikadon is whether the other side when we
say זכין zachin like he's sort of like take possession of it
to prevent the guy from backing out but not enough so that
the guy's off the hook of having paid off his debt yet.
So that was like one discussion. And then we're dealing with this
case about a person who's giving away a gift and he's saying
הולך holech this 100 dollars to somebody or he's a שכיב מרע
sh'chiv mera whatever and there the גמרא Gemara is trying to push
for the idea that הולך holech is לאו כזכי lav k'zachi is
that it would not take effect for the other guy and if
it turns out that the messenger found that the guy had died
maybe it goes back to the original sender. So that's an important
question which is one minute we did a whole סוגיא sugya that
הולך holech was כזכי k'zachi and here we're basically assuming הולך holech
is not כזכי k'zachi and unless it's a שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera
case the money goes back to the sender. So I so that
was sort of a question we raised yesterday and תוספות Tosafos a
few דף daf earlier address that question and תוספות Tosafos basically say
that it re- it does depend on whether it's a gift or
whether it's paying back a debt. When it's a gift when it's
paying back a debt and there's more of a sense that like
you know תוספות Tosafos doesn't spell it out but it seems to
be that if there's a sense that that money is owed we're
going to interpret your הולך holech you know either say psychologically they're
more committed to paying it up because you owe that money or
it's just because legally you want the other side to get the
money that's coming to them we are going to interpret that הולך
holech as being כזכי k'zachi when you owe the money. So that
was the first סוגיא sugya by the case of the debt or
the פקדון. pikadon. Whereas the סוגיא sugya we're dealing with now where
it's a one-sided gift and the other side is less deserving of
the money we're going to actually say we're
not going to
you know we're pushing in the
opposite direction to say that unless it's a case of
שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera where interpret
הולך holech as
כזכי k'zachi it's לאו כזכי lav k'zachi and that's the סוגיא sugya
we're in the middle of. The other thing that came up yesterday
that I looked into is that it also assumes that even in
a case of a שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera the guy is giving
the gift and then he's on his deathbed and then it turns
out that the other side is dead when he gave this the
gift the גמרא Gemara says well was the other side alive when
when the gift was being given or not. And the question is
one minute but who cares? Because if the reason the other side
gets it is that it was a case of שכיב מרע sh'chiv
mera but a שכיב מרע's sh'chiv mera words only take effect at
the death of the person on the deathbed. So therefore even if
the other side was alive when the person was gifting the money
as a שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera if he was dead before the
giver died then the gift was already nullified because the gift only
takes effect when the giver dies. So there's a question that תוספות
Tosafos raises and the answer's not fully satisfying but I wanted to
show you the answer because it is a problem in the סוגיא.
sugya. So take a look at the little תוספות Tosafos on יד
עמוד ב. yud dalet amud bet. הא בשכיב מרע, Ha b'sh'chiv mera,
the first תוספות, Tosafos, he says אומר ר"י Omer Ri אף על
גב דמית מקבל בחיי נותן, af al gav d'meis mekabel b'chayei nosen,
even though the receiver died before the giver died, ולא קני אלא
לאחר מיתת נותן, velo kani ela achar misas nosen, and we know
that a שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera words are only effective at the
death of the שכיב מרע. sh'chiv mera. So what good does it
do? You know it says well as long as the receiver was
alive when the gift was being given then the money would go
to his heirs. What good does that do? The gift only takes
effect when the giver dies, okay? אפילו הכי קנו ירשין. afilu hachi
kanu yarshin.
Nevertheless, thank you, thank you so much, the heirs of the receiver
take possession דדעת נותן הוא דכיון שישנו למקבל בשעת מתנה dedaas nosen
hu d'keivan sheyeshno l'mekabel b'shas masnos
because what the שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera wants, wherever he is he's
on his deathbed and he's gifting this money, he wants that if
the guy is alive right now at the moment that he's gifting
it, okay, שיזכה מקבל אחר מיתתו או הוא או ירשיו. sheyizke mekabel
achar misaso o hu o yarshav. He wants the other side to
take possession after his death, either he or his heirs. the הרא"ש
Rash leaves it as a
צריך עיון, tzarich iyun, okay, but I don't
want, I'm not here to give an answer, I'm here to raise
a question, okay? So those are two wrap-up points from yesterday. Number
one, on עמוד א' amud aleph we assumed הולך כזכאי, holech k'zachai,
now we're dealing with a case of a guy giving a gift
and we're assuming הולך לאו כזכאי holech lav k'zachai and תוספות Tosafot
says well when it's a gift and you don't owe the other
side the money, we're going to interpret הולך holech with more reservation
as לאו כזכאי, lav k'zachai, and the other is why we assume
that if it's a case of שכיב מרע, shachiv mera, the other
side gets it if he's alive when it's being given, if the
receiver's alive when it's being given, since the שכיב מרע's shachiv mera
gift usually only takes effect when the שכיב מרע shachiv mera dies.
Okay, so that's a question that the ראשונים Rishonim grapple with, so
I just didn't want to, I don't have any good answer to
that, but I wanted to at least acknowledge that that was a
question. Let's continue now with the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says
לימא, leima, so that's fifteen lines before the lines get wide, first
word is לימא, leima, לימא הולך כזכאי תנאי,
leima holech
k'zachai tanna'ei, let's say this is a debate of תנאים, tanna'im, this
will be a little חזרה chazarah about what we did yesterday because
the scenario will be almost the exact same, okay? And this is
a case of הולך כזכאי holech k'zachai by a gift, which is
more
debatable, okay? דתניא, d'tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, baraita, הולך מנה
holech mane or הולך מנה לפלוני, holach mane liploni, go bring, convey
this hundred dollars to so and so, it's a gift, והלך ובקשו
ולא מצאו, v'halach u'biksho v'lo m'tza'o, he went to find the person
and he was no longer
around, he died, okay,
ולא מצאו, v'lo m'tza'o, יחזרו למשלח, yachzeru l'mishaleach, give it back to
the משלח, mishaleach, okay, מת המשלח, met mishaleach, now what happens if
the משלח mishaleach is dead?
רבי נתן ורבי יעקב אמרו Rabbi Natan v'Rabbi Yaakov amru
יחזרו ליורשי המשלח, yachzeru l'yorshei mishaleach, fine, give it back to his
heirs, which is essentially the same פסק psak as give it back
to the משלח. mishaleach. ויש אומרים ליורשי מי שנשתלח לו, v'yesh omrim
l'yorshei mi shenishtalach lo, no, it goes to the heirs of the
receiver, which that ויש אומרים yesh omrim presumably would say that in
the first case as well even if the משלח mishaleach was alive.
Okay, so now you've got the idea, let's sort of put them
on the board because the גמרא's Gemara going
to, okay, so we got a
guy, this is the משלח, mishaleach, he's sending a הולך מנה, holach
mane,
he's sending it with the hand of somebody else as a שליח,
shaliach, and to this guy, he's
dead,
okay,
the מי שנשתלח לו,
mi shenishtalach
lo,
okay, alright, so what do you do with the money? And here's
the pile of money,
what are you going to do with all that money? That's my
pile, anyway, okay, so the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says
יחזרו
למשלח,
yachzeru
l'mishaleach, okay, next opinion says, what's the opinion? רבי נתן ורבי יעקב
אמרו ליורשי המשלח,
Rabbi Natan v'Rabbi Yaakov
amru l'yorshei mishaleach, רבי אלעזר ורבי נתן
Rabbi Elazar
v'Rabbi Natan which are essentially
the
same, right? Because יורשי המשלח, yorshei mishaleach,
hold on, Henry isn't talking about, I know, he isn't talking about
that scenario, but essentially it's משלח, mishaleach, okay, that's really one position,
and then what's the next position? ויש אומרים ליורשי מי שנשתלח לו,
v'yesh omrim l'yorshei mi shenishtalach lo,
is that רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, ויש אומרים? yesh omrim? No, it's
usually רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, ויש אומרים ליורשי מי שנשתלח
לו,
yesh omrim
l'yorshei mi shenishtalach lo, okay,
so this basically says this side, number one says the other side
didn't get it, let's just anticipate what the גמרא's Gemara going to
say, הולך לאו כזכאי, holech lav k'zachai,
this side assumes the other side got it, you give them the
hundred dollars, she's dead, who cares? The other side got it, okay,
so hopefully it's assuming he died after the money was given over,
if he died before then it would have been בטל, batel, anyway
that's probably הולך כזכאי, holech k'zachai, okay,
now we're not done though, we have a couple more opinions, okay,
רבי יהודה הנשיא אומר משום רבי יעקב שאמר משום רבי מאיר Rabbi
Yehuda HaNasi omer mishum Rabbi Yaakov she'amar mishum Rabbi Meir מצוה לקיים
דברי המת, mitzvah l'kayem divrei hamet, now מצוה לקיים דברי המת, mitzvah
l'kayem divrei hamet, the
משלח mishaleach
because this is the case that the משלח mishaleach died, right? מת
המשלח, met hamishaleach, so מצוה לקיים
דברי המת mitzvah l'kayem divrei hamet sounds
like number two, well no, I mean it might result
in the same but it sounds like in principle הולך holech is
לאו כזכאי, lav k'zachai,
the other side doesn't own it right away, right? Right? But, but
מצוה לקיים, mitzvah l'kayem, so effectively it'll be like number two, right?
The other side will get it but not because he was got
it when he took possession of it, only because now you have
an obligation to do the wish of the guy that, if the
guy... I was alive, you'd give him the money back. Because he
died, there's a special obligation to satisfy the bequest of somebody, you
know, of somebody's wishes before they you
who communicated wishes and then died.
Everything from where you underpin's with שכיב מרע? shechiv mera?
No. First of all, there's a whole long discussion in תוספות Tosafot
that we don't always say מצווה לקיים דברי המת. mitzvah l'kayem divrei
hamet. We might only say it in cases like this where money
was given over for that purpose, right? To somebody who was already
holding on money that somebody had wished to go to somebody else
and then the person died. You know, if the guy was just
סתם stam money in his bank account and he wasn't a שכיב
מרע. shechiv mera. And this applies even if the guy commanded it
when he was well. שכיב מרע shechiv mera applies only if the
guy's on his deathbed. שכיב מרע shechiv mera takes effect automatically. מצווה
לקיים mitzvah l'kayem creates an obligation, but it is not automatically legally
effective. So there's like all these differences. Okay, but yes, it results
in something similar.
Distinct differences. Right.
Exactly. Okay. חכמים אומרים יחלוקו chachamim omrim yachloku and כאן אמרו kahn
amru which presumably means בן בתירה Ben Batera said, כל מה שירצה
שליח יעשה. kol mah sheyirtzeh shaliach ya'aseh. Okay,
which is basically a case of a type of ספק safeik which
has two possibilities: either יחלוקו yachloku or מה שירצה שליח. mah sheyirtzeh
shaliach. Now
we'll discuss that in a minute, but let's first identify what these
different cases are. So it looks like this is the straight debate.
Okay. So this here is the case of ספק. safeik. Do we
go like this way or this way, so let's just split it
or let the שליח shaliach decide, dealer's choice. So
the גמרא Gemara says... okay. אמר רבי שמעון בן ננסי, amar Rabbi
Shimon ben Nansi, אוי בי היה מעשה, oy bi hayah ma'aseh, I
had a case just like this, ויאמרו יעשו ליורשי המשלח. ve'ameru ya'asu
l'yorshei hameshaleach. And they basically wound up
paskening like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer or רבי ננסי Rabbi Nansi up
there. Okay.
Now מאי לאו אקמיפלגי, mai lav akamipalgi, let's say this is the
debate. The תנא קמא tanna kamma סבר savar הולך לאו כזכי, holach
lav kizchi, check.
So therefore it always goes back to the משלח. meshaleach. הולך לאו
כזכי. holach lav kizchi. רבי ננסי, Rabbi Nansi, רבי ננס, Rabbi Nanos,
רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov nanu הולך כזכי, holach kizchi, ואף על גב
דמית לא אמרינן מצווה לקיים דברי המת. ve'af al gav demet lo
amrinan mitzvah l'kayem divrei hamet. What do רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
רבי ננסי Rabbi Nansi add when they say it goes back to
his heirs? They say yes, הולך הוא לאו כזכי holach hu lav
kizchi and we're going to disagree with number three, even if he
died there's no מצווה לקיים דברי המת. mitzvah l'kayem divrei hamet. So
it goes back here and there's no מצווה לקיים, mitzvah l'kayem, הולך
לאו כזכי. holach lav kizchi. Okay. ויש אומרים הולך כזכי. ve'yesh omrim
holach kizchi. ויש
אומרים yesh omrim says the other side gets it. So הולך כזכי,
holach kizchi, יורשי מי שנשתלחו אצלו. yorshei mi shenishtalchu etzlo. רבי יהודה
ננסי Rabbi Yehuda Nansi אומר משום רבי יעקב omer mishum Rabbi Yaakov
שם משום רבי מאיר shem mishum Rabbi Meir הולך לאו כזכי. holach
lav kizchi. Fundamentally it's not
כזכי, kizchi, it deserves to go back to the משלח, meshaleach, but
היכא דמית, heicha de'mit,
if the משלח meshaleach died, אמרינן מצווה לקיים דברי המת. amrinan mitzvah
l'kayem divrei hamet. So the other side doesn't own it yet, but
it would be a good idea to fulfill like it's important, you
know, you're supposed to do the wishes of the משלח. meshaleach. Okay,
but technically the other side doesn't own it. Okay. וחכמים אומרים יחלוקו.
ve'chachamim omrim yachloku. The variety of ספק... safeik... they have a doubt.
וכאן אמרו שודא עדיף. ve'kahn amru shuda adif. It's better to just
pick one side. Now having picked one side, if you look in
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says
מה שירצה שליח יעשה. mah sheyirtzeh shaliach ya'aseh. רש"י Rashi in that
like between the in the space between the bottom of the גליון
הש"ס Gilyon HaShas and the left in the next bracketed marginal note,
רש"י Rashi says or right before the next marginal, מה שירצה שליח
יעשה, mah sheyirtzeh shaliach ya'aseh, לפי מה שראה בדעתו של משלח אם
היה עינו יפה במתנה זו או במקבל והזמנה. lefi mah she'ra'ah beda'ato
shel meshaleach im haya eino yafa bematanah zu o bamakabel ve'hazmaman. Basically
you try to do your best job in assessing, you don't know
whether it goes back or doesn't go back, you know, do you
say הולך כזכי holach kizchi or not? So you do your best
job to not to figure out the law because we don't know
the law but to act in accordance with what you think would
be the wishes of the person who had given you the money.
That's the way רש"י Rashi says. תוספות Tosafot says there's an important
question, look at תוספות, Tosafot, look at two תוספות Tosafots for a
moment. חכמים אומרים יחלוקו. chachamim omrim yachloku.
So what do you do if you don't know where the money
goes? You split it. תוספות Tosafot says כל תיקו
שבש"ס, kol teiku shebaShas, anytime the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, right,
which is we don't know what the הלכה halacha is, מפורש בשערים
דרבינו האי דחולקים. meforash beshearim de'Rabbeinu Hai decholkim.
So this book of רבינו האי גאון Rabbeinu Hai Gaon says if
there's a תיקו teiku and it's a ממונות mammonus issue, you split
the money. Okay. ואין נראה לי אלא היכא דאשכחן בהדיא יחלוקו. ve'ein
nireh li ela heicha de'aska mehedia yachloku.
No, if the גמרא Gemara explicitly says you don't know what the
הלכה halacha is and you split it, we do it, but otherwise
דאדרבה אמרינן אוקים ממונא בחזקת מריה. de'aderabba omrim okim mammona bechezkat marei.
Otherwise we would say no, you know, the person who's in possession
of the money holds onto it and המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi
mechavero alav hara'ayah.
Here it's a little different because the שליח's shaliach in possession of
the money and we don't know whose money he's in possession of,
right? You understand? Because im הולך כזכי holach kizchi he's in possession
of this guy and if הולך holach is not כזכי kizchi he's
in possession of the משלח. meshaleach. So here it makes a lot
of sense יחלוקו. yachloku. Now what's the idea of שודא? shuda? וכאן
אמרו שודא עדיף. ve'kahn amru shuda adif. מכאן מדקדק רבינו
תם. mikan medakdek Rabbeinu Tam. So that was a question where somebody
had written out a gift to somebody and there were two people
with the same name and you didn't know who he had given
the gift to. And let's say all other circumstances were equal like
there's no way to say well who was his friend who you
know who was his business associate like there's not there's none of
that to go on and the גמרא Gemara said well you do
שודא. shuda. So what does רש"י Rashi say שודא shuda means? דהיינו
שידקדק הדיין מי היה אוהב יותר ומי היה רגיל אצלו ויתן. Dehainu
sheyidakdek hadayan mi haya ohev yoter umi haya ragil etzlo veyiten. So
you try to just assess based on your knowledge of the circumstances,
you make your best judgment. וכן בכאן נמי פירש קונטרס כמו התם.
V'chen b'chan nami peresh kuntres k'mo hatam. And that's what רש"י Rashi
says here too, the שליח shaliach tries to decide whether he would
want to give the gift in this circumstance. Okay, אלא, ela, but
רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says that's wrong because here it's like there's
no nothing to base it on. The guy wanted to give the
gift and then he died.
So תוספות Tosafot says there's no nothing to base this decision on.
אלא יהא הדיין למי שירצה, Ela yehe hadayan l'mi sheyirtze, just just
whichever one you want to do, just כי הכא דקאמר מה שירצה
שליח יעשה ki hacha d'ka'amar ma sheyirtze shaliach ya'aseh because the תוספות
Tosafot particularly emphasized the phrase, do what you want. Okay. Maybe give
it to the guy who's poorer, who could use the money more.
Okay, it's interesting, right? You try to make when when making a
decision based on the law doesn't work, you know, you try to
make it based on the guy's desire, will, intent, or do you
sort of say no, you have nothing to go on and then
you make it on a policy decision? Like who deserves the money
more, you know, who could use the money, you know, you know,
who could use the money more? Or maybe you just do something
arbitrary? So that's quite fascinating the possibilities of what what the שודא
shuda means. But that's particularly in this case also where nobody is
in possession of it. Yes.
Somebody always has to be in possession of the money, right?
It can't be... Well this is a third party is in possession.
Okay. And he doesn't know if he's holding on to it for
which side. No, but can't be can't when the when the agent
has the money the possession is suspended or something in...
Well the possession is in doubt who's considered to be in possession.
But somebody is.
Somebody is, the agent is.
But someone has to be legally, somebody has to be.
He just... but no but we don't know who that person is.
Is he holding on to for side A or for side B?
But right. Okay. So now back to the גמרא. Gemara. So this
seems to be a clear debate about whether about whether הולך כזוכי
holach k'zochi or not. Yes and yeah okay yeah.
Wait, I'm sorry, I
thought we said that if the person had died we would give
them the money back? I thought we said yesterday if the person
hadn't died we'd give the money to the receiver's heirs for sure.
If this guy had died...
if the giver hadn't died we'd give the money to the receiver's
heirs.
That's but that's what's being debated. These two positions say no. I
mean, you would go back to the משלח. meshaleach. That's what the
גמרא Gemara is saying, this is look exactly that. This is a
debate what we were discussing yesterday of הולך כזוכי holach k'zochi seems
to be exactly this debate.
So I'm sorry if if the giver's A the receiver's B. In
the case where B dies but A is alive.
So according to תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar
you give it back to the משלח. meshaleach. According to יש אומרים
yesh omrim you give it to this guy's heirs. That's exactly the
debate. Okay. So isn't this exactly what we were discussing yesterday which
is what the
גמרא Gemara says? So the גמרא Gemara says okay. רבי שמעון בן
ננס מעשה אתא לאשמועינן. Rebbi Shimon ben Nanas ma'aseh ata l'ashmueinan. He's
just telling us a story. So isn't that what's going on? So
the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no, בבריא דכולי עלמא לא פליגי.
b'bari d'kulei alma lo peligi. If the guy was healthy we would
always say... we would always say הולך לאו כזוכי. holach lav k'zochi.
So again, as opposed to what we said on the עמוד א
amud aleph by a debt, by מתנה matana where we want to
assume הולך לאו כזוכי. holach lav k'zochi. So here you have though
three positions, תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, רבי אלעזר, Rebbi Elazar, רבי שמעון
בן ננס, Rebbi Shimon ben Nanas, and this third one here that
all say הולך... holach oh actually that works. All these positions say
הולך holach לאו כזוכי which is what we want to say. But
we're going now neutralize even number two that says הולך כזוכי. holach
k'zochi. So we're going to say if the guy was healthy everybody
would agree that הולך holach was לאו כזוכי. Okay. בבריא דכולי עלמא
לא פליגי הכא מאי עסקינן בשכיב מרע. B'bari d'kulei alma lo peligi
hacha mai askinan b'shchiv mera.
We're talking about the case that the משלח meshaleach is on his
deathbed. Evidence being that he dies in the most in the scenarios
in the ברייתא. braita. And therefore the only position here that... therefore
number two that says הולך כזוכי holach k'zochi that it works is
not because of הולך כזוכי. holach k'zochi. The reason it worked here
was because this guy was on his deathbed in שכיב מרע. shchiv
mera. Whatever שכיב מרע shchiv mera says takes effect. But the problem
is now what about the other one? Everybody who says it didn't
work. Isn't שכיב מרע shchiv mera supposed to automatically take effect? So
now we're going to pull out of our hat a position that
doesn't buy into the whole idea of שכיב מרע. shchiv mera. So
we're going to really make this whole thing very convoluted as a
way of getting out of the idea that anybody would hold הולך
כזוכי. holach k'zochi. Okay. Some of the Hebrew...
if the person is healthy what?
Then if the person is healthy then everybody would agree that it
does not go to the other side. That whole that הולך לאו
כזכי holach lav k'zachi and it doesn't go to the other side.
And it goes back
to the guy who gave it? Goes back to the guy who
gave it. To the A. The only reason
that position two says it goes to the other side is because
it was a case of שכיב מרע. shchiv mera. All right? So
שכיב מרע, shchiv mera, it would look like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
רבנן. Rabbanan. Let me see, it's not. המחלק נכסיו על פי, Hamchalek
nichasav al pi, somebody is distributing orally distributing, verbally distributing his property
and he's on his deathbed. רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, well we'll see
about that. רבי אליעזר אומר אחד בריא ואחד שכיב מרע, Rabbi Eliezer
omer echad bari v'echad shechiv mera, whether he's healthy, whether he's in
danger of losing his life, he's on his deathbed. נכסים שיש להם
אחריות, Nichasim sheyesh lahem achrayus, if the things that are real estate,
they're נקנים בכסף בשטר ובחזקה, niknim b'kesef b'shtar u'v'chazakah, you have to
do a normal קניין kinyan of with money or with the writ
or with things possession. ושאין להם אחריות V'she'ein lahem achrayus chattel, אינן
נקנין אלא במשיכה, einan niknin ela bimshichah, you have to draw them.
I mean, I don't care if the guy's on his deathbed. You
want to distribute your property, you have to do a קניין. kinyan.
וחכמים אומרים אלו ואלו נקנים באמירה. V'chachamim omrim eilu v'eilu niknim b'amirah.
No, if the guy's on his deathbed, then whether it's real estate
or chattel, just the words make it take effect. Okay. אמרו לו,
Amru lo, they said to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, מעשה באמן של
בני רוכל, Maaseh b'iman shel bnei Rocheil, there was a story about
the mother of Rachel of the children of רוכל, Rocheil, שהייתה חולה,
shehaytah cholah, she was ill and basically on her deathbed, ואמרה תנו
בינסי לבתי, v'amrah tnu binasi l'viti, give my בינסי, binasi, which I
think is like what type of something like a, what do you
call it, a tiara or something. Anyway, to my daughter. ועמה שנים
עשר מנה, V'iman shneim asar maneh, it was very expensive, twelve hundred
pounds, okay. ומתה, v'meisah,
and she died. וקיימו חכמים את דבריה, V'kiymu chachamim et dvareha, and
the חכמים chachamim did what she requested, so you see it was
a deathbed bequest and you see it takes effect. אמר להם, Amar
lahem, he said back to them, בני רוכל תקברם אמם, Bnei Rocheil
tikvrem imam, the children of רוכל, Rocheil, their mother should bury them.
Meaning, who the heck cares about the children of רוכל? Rocheil? So
רש"י Rashi basically says that if you look at רש"י, Rashi, כלום
היא כלום לא יעלה על לב ולא יזכר בבית המדרש, Klum hi
klum lo ya'aleh al lev v'lo yizacher b'beit hamidrash, I don't even
want to talk about those kids, לראיה
לפי
שרשעים היו.
l'rayah l'fi sherishaim
hayu. We have this case at least four times.
I know. לפי שרשעים היו שהיו מקיימים כלאים בכרמם, L'fi sherishaim hayu
shehayu mekaymim kilayim b'karman, and רבי אליעזר קילאן Rabbi Eliezer kila'an ממנו,
mimeinu, okay,
basically they were, you know, they kept כלאים kilayim growing in their
garden. ולא נמנעם מן הראיה. V'lo nimnem min hara'ayah. Okay, now that's
all very nice, but the חכמים chachamim did what they wanted, okay.
But the point is, he said look, but what they did when
they wanted was they gave away a very precious possession of their
mother to other people. So maybe it's not because that was really
the הלכה, halachah, maybe it's because we don't really care about the
kids, the kids were רשעים, rishaim, so we were happy to do
what the mother wanted, okay. Anyway, that's the edge of it.
אמר להם מבני רוכל, Amar lahem m'bnei Rocheil,
they didn't give them nothing. They gave what their mother's possession to
somebody else. Right? Oh, no, she said לבתי, l'viti, as opposed to
my son.
Ah,
so daughters weren't with him?
Yeah, I think so. Okay.
But doesn't the law apply whether they're wicked or not? If...
Yeah, what can I tell you? Okay, anyway, the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אמר להם בני רוכל, Amar lahem bnei Rocheil, okay, anyway,
תקברם אמם. tikvrem imam. Okay, תנא קמא כרבי אליעזר, Tanna Kamma k'Rabbi
Eliezer, so basically it's a debate whether we say דברי שכיב מרע
divrei shchiv mera works. So now basically here, basically see mostly הולך
לאו כזכי. holach lav k'zachi. One position said it did work and
went to the other side. Rather than acknowledge there's one position that
says it works, we're going to say everybody says it doesn't work.
The positions that say the other side gets it is because it's
a שכיב מרע shchiv mera case. Okay, I'm sorry, what it says
the other side gets it, number two, is because it's a שכיב
מרע shchiv mera case and these positions that say the other side
doesn't get it denies that שכיב מרע's shchiv mera effective. All right?
So תנא קמא כרבי אליעזר, Tanna Kamma k'Rabbi Eliezer, so the side
that the other side doesn't get it, A holds הולך holach is
not כזכי, k'zachi, and number two, שכיב מרע shchiv mera doesn't work.
רבי יהודה בן בתירה נמי כרבי אליעזר, Rabbi Yehudah ben Beseira nami
k'Rabbi Eliezer, אף על גב דמיתה אמרינן מצווה לקיים דברי המת, af
al gav d'meisah amrinan mitzvah l'kayem divrei hameis, and not only does
it not work as a שכיב מרע, shchiv mera, it doesn't work
because of מצווה לקיים דברי אמירה. mitzvah l'kayem divrei amirah. ויש אומרים
כרבנן, V'yesh omrim k'rabbanan, ויש אומרים v'yesh omrim that says the other
side gets it is not because הולך holach is כזכי, k'zachi, הולך
is not כזכי. k'zachi. It's because the guy was a שכיב מרע,
shchiv mera, okay. ורבי יהודה הנשיא שאמר משום רבי מאיר כרבי אליעזר.
V'Rabbi Yehudah Hanasi she'amar mishum Rabbi Meir k'Rabbi Eliezer. So רבי יהודה
הנשיא Rabbi Yehudah Hanasi said it doesn't work as שכיב מרע, shchiv
mera, the other side doesn't get it automatically. מיהו היכא דמת, Mihu
heicha d'meis, once the giver dies, אמרינן מצווה לקיים דברי המת, amrinan
mitzvah l'kayem divrei hameis, then there's a מצווה mitzvah to do it.
וחכמים אומרים יחלוקו מספקא להו, V'chachamim omrim yachloku missafek lahu, they don't
know, so you split it. וחד אמר שודא דדייני, V'chad amar shuda
d'dayni, ורבי שמעון הנשיא מטא אטלא לאשמועינן, v'Rabbi Shimon Hanasi mata atlah
l'ashmunin, שכוייח. shkoich. Okay, so bottom line is the simple debate clearly
was whether הולך is כזכי k'zachi and even here most of the
positions hold or at least these two hold it's לאו כזכי. lav
k'zachi. This one holds a ספק, safek, but rather than acknowledge that
there's a position of הולך כזכי, holach k'zachi, we said if anything
is working here, it's working because of שכיב מרע. shchiv mera. Okay,
so we so do not want to acknowledge if there's a position
by a gift of הולך כזכי. holach k'zachi. So what which is
why the if Michael was bothered with what's the הלכה, halachah, the
general assumption is that by a מתנה, matanah, הולך is לאו כזכי
lav k'zachi because the גמרא Gemara is so committed to denying that
position. Yeah, exactly. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara just ends by
saying רבי שמעון הנשיא מטא. Rabbi Shimon Hanasi mata. איבעיא להו, Iba'yu
lahu, they raised the question, רבי שמעון הנשיא נשיא הוא, Rabbi Shimon
Hanasi nasi hu, was he a נשיא? nasi? It says... שמעון הנשיא,
Shimon HaNasi, או שמי דנשיא קאמר? O shemi deNasi ka'amar? Is it
like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says in the name of the נשיא?
Nasi? Usually תוספות Tosafot says, because תוספות Tosafot says, because תוספות Tosafot
says, we've never heard of a רבי שמעון הנשיא. Rabbi Shimon HaNasi.
So תא שמע דאמר רבי, Ta shema de'amar Rabbi, רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, הלכה רבי שמעון הנשיא. Halacha Rabbi Shimon HaNasi. There you go,
according to that we rule like רבי שמעון הנשיא. Rabbi Shimon HaNasi.
רבי שמעון הנשיא Rabbi Shimon HaNasi was like the first position, which
is הולך לאו כזכי Holech lav kizchi and goes back to the
giver, which is הולך לאו כזכי Holech lav kizchi and goes back
to the giver. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אידי דאיבעיא להו,
idai d'ibaia lehu, so we want to know נשיא הוא או דקאמר
משמי דנשיא, Nasi hu o d'ka'amar meshmei d'Nasi, till we answer our
question תיקו, Teiku, we don't know fine. גופא אמר רב יוסף הלכה
רבי שמעון הנשיא. Gufa amar Rav Yosef halacha Rabbi Shimon HaNasi. וקיימא
לן דברי שכיב מרע ככתובים וכמסורים דמו. Ve'ka'imalan Divrei Shchiv Mer kechisuvin
u'kmsurin damu. That's fine to say like we rule like רבי שמעון
הנשיא Rabbi Shimon HaNasi and it goes back to the giver if
we're talking about a normal case, then we're just saying הולך לאו
כזכי Holech lav kizchi and goes back to the giver. But if
we were talking about a שכיב מרע shchiv mera case, how can
you say we rule it goes back to the giver? Don't we
say that the שכיב מרע shchiv mera words are binding? So the
גמרא Gemara says רב יוסף מוקי לה בברי. Rav Yosef muki lah
bebari. Okay he doesn't buy into your whole read. He says it
was talking about a ברי, bari, a healthy person. והא יורשי משלח
קאמר? Ve'ha iyorshei m'shelach ka'iman d'ka'amar? Okay that's fine that goes back
to the giver, we're talking about a healthy person like the פשט
pshat of that ברייתא. braita. ופסקינן הולך לאו כזכי Ve'paskinun Holech Lav
Kizchi so it goes back to the giver. The only problem is
when the giver is dead, why would רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say
it would go back to the giver? What about מצוה לקיים דברי
המת? Mitzvah Lekayem Divrei HaMeis? וקיימא לן מצוה לקיים דברי המת? Ve'ka'imalan
Mitzvah Lekayem Divrei HaMeis? So what about that? So תני יחזירו למשלח,
tani yachziru lameshalach, fine. When רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says goes back,
he should not be saying goes back to the heirs of the
giver, he should basically be saying goes back to the משלח, meshaleach,
the giver, if the giver is still alive. But if the giver
had genuinely died, we would say מצוה לקיים דברי המת, Mitzvah Lekayem
Divrei HaMeis, which means what? Which means basically we פסקן pasken this
middle position. We פסקן pasken by a מתנה, matanah, הולך לאו כזכי,
Holech lav kizchi, by a מתנה. matanah.
So therefore if this guy is dead, then it goes back to
the giver because הולך לאו כזכי. Holech lav kizchi. But if the
giver dies, then it would be an issue of מצוה לקיים דברי
המת Mitzvah Lekayem Divrei HaMeis and then he would go ahead and
do the wishes of the dead. הדרן לך המביא, Hadran lach hameivi,
that was a fun little discussion there at the end, having not
too much to do with גיטין, Gittin, but now you see why
גיטין Gittin is such a nice מסכת masechet that gets learned in
the ישיבות yeshivas because it can very easily move on to other
larger discussions, okay, about זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin l'adam shelo b'fanav,
דברי שכיב מרע, divrei shchiv mera, מצוה לקיים דברי המת, mitzvah lekayem
divrei hameis, הולך כזכי, holech kizchi, right, all of these other like
major concepts.
And it goes to the, if the giver dies it goes to
either the receiver or the receiver's heirs? If the giver dies, well
we פסקן pasken הולך לאו כזכי. Holech lav kizchi. So if the
giver dies it goes back to the giver's heirs, right?
Because if the giver dies and the receiver dies, if either of
them die? Because since הולך לאו כזכי Holech lav kizchi when the
שליח shaliach has the money, it's still totally in the possession of
the משלח. meshaleach. If the משלח meshaleach dies, then the gift is
בטל batel unless you say מצוה לקיים דברי המת, Mitzvah Lekayem Divrei
HaMeis, but in terms of ownership, it never gets owned
by the other side until the other side receives it.
Okay, so if the
giver dies it's irrelevant.
Right.
Interesting to think about what the implications would be about this nowadays
in terms of like mail. Like imagine ראובן Reuven mailed something to
somebody, okay, and then in the three days it took to arrive,
ראובן Reuven died in the interim. Could the heirs say, well you
know we're asking for it back because by the time you received
it our father was dead and therefore it was already ours when
it was in the mail, right? I don't think so. My guess
is that as soon as you drop it in the mail, there's
a delivery rule.
Well there's a thing in contracts as soon
as you mail it it belongs to the other side
at least for delivery.
But you could be responsible if the other side doesn't get it,
right? Like I never received my gift I want my money back,
like it's complicated, it's a similar type of an
issue. It's sort of like what we learned on the עמוד א
amud aleph yesterday, which is you can't be חוזר chozer once it's
in the mail, but the other side hasn't received it until they've
received it, right? It's a funny sort of middle type of a
reality. That would be an interesting question. What?
Can an heir cash a check for somebody who died anyway? Any
kind of check. Like a paycheck. Can an heir in civil law?
Yeah I assume that goes to the estate. All right, anyway, let's
take a look now. Back to בפני נכתב. befanai nichtav. Remember בפני
נכתב? befanai nichtav? What's so funny about this is like this seems
to be a very secondary תקנה, takanah, right, and so much, like
it's a דרבנן, derabbanan, and so much of all of the original
material in the opening פרקים prakim is about this דרבנן. derabbanan. Now
it does get to core issues about חתימת הגט chasimat haget and
so on, but so much about it is focusing on this phenomenon.
Let's take a look. המביא גט ממדינת הים, Hameivi get mimedinat hayam,
so somebody is bringing this גט get from overseas. ואמר, Ve'amar, and
says בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. Befanai nichtav uvefanai nechtam. בפני נכתב אבל
לא בפני נחתם, Befanai nichtav aval lo befanai nechtam, it was written
in front of me
but it wasn't signed. Or בפני נחתם אבל לא בפני נכתב, Befanai
nechtam aval lo befanai nichtav,
it was signed in front of me but not written. Now again,
we're going to assume in this משנה mishnah like רבה Rabbah which
is the easier assumption that it's fundamentally about קיום השטר, kiyum hashtar,
which is pretty much the conclusion. Of your of your פרק. perek.
So if you said it was signed and not written maybe there
would be a הוה אמינא hava amina that that would be good
because it really is about the signing. Or if he says בפני
נכתב כולו bifanay nechtav kulo it was all written in front of
me ובפני נחתם חציו uvfanay nechtam chetzyo but only the first signature
was done in front of me. או בפני נכתב חציו O bifanay
nechtav chetzyo half was written in front of me ובפני נחתם כולו
uvfanay nechtam kulo and all was signed. That would be the best.
If it was all signed you saw both signatures. The only reason
you'll remember according to רבא Rava that you say בפני נכתב bifanay
nechtav is so that you signal that this is not a normal
קיום שטרות. kiyum shtaros. Normal קיום שטרות kiyum shtaros requires two. This
is a special תקנה. takkana. So you make that clear by testifying
to the fact that you were present at the writing which shows
that this is something of a different nature. So if you only
testify there for half the writing you would think that would be
okay. You were there for all the signing and half the writing.
Nevertheless in all of those cases פסול. pasul. It's invalid. You need
to do the whole תקנה takkana exactly right and you need to
be present fully for the writing and the signing. Okay, הכי קתני
hachi katani basically. אחד אומר
בפני נכתב ואחד אומר בפני נחתם. Echad omer bifanay nechtav v'echad omer
bifanay nechtam. Now let's say you have two people bring you the
שטר shtar again. One says I saw it written and the other
says I saw it signed. פסול, pasul, it's פסול. pasul. Now if
one of them isn't the שליח shliach it's obviously פסול. pasul. The
שליח shliach
has to do both. But if they're both שלוחים shluchim why can't
you look at them as a unit? So nevertheless that's the חידוש
chidush that even so the even though the שליח shliach is saying
בפני נכתב bifanay nechtav in order to make the בפני נחתם bifanay
nechtam distinct and not normal קיום שטרות, kiyum shtaros, right, in order
to allow it to work with this special תקנה, takkana, the person
who is testifying to that has to be also testifying to the
writing. It's not enough that someone else is testifying to the writing.
Okay. שנים אומרים בפנינו נכתב ואחד אומר בפני נחתם. Shnayim omrim befanenu
nechtav v'echad omer bifanay nechtam.
Two people say it was written in front of us but a
third guy says it was signed. פסול, pasul, who cares? שכוח, Shkayach,
you know better that it was written but that's not really the
point. Now רבי יהודה מכשיר. Rebbi Yehuda machshir. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
says it's כשר kasher and the גמרא Gemara
says not only on this case but the earlier cases as well
where is if one person says it was written and one person
says it was signed or two people says it was written. As
long as you're having testimony to the signing and the writing even
if it's not the same person for רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda that's
okay. Now אחד אומר בפני נכתב ושנים אומרים בפנינו נחתם. Echad omer
bifanay nechtav ushnayim omrim befanenu nechtam.
One person says it was written and two people say it was
signed. כשר, kasher, that's כשר kasher for the obvious reason that if
two people are testifying to the signatures it's a normal קיום שטר.
kiyum shtar. Okay. So again I'm not going to we're not going
to worry how this works for רבא Rava who's concerned about לשמה,
lishma, let's just focus on the קיום שטרות kiyum shtaros and it
makes the whole discussion so much easier. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא.
Gemara. Sometimes though you didn't want to make
this a normal קיום שטר. kiyum shtar. Yeah, but it could be.
The גמרא Gemara has always said that if you can't say or
you don't say the בפני נחתם bifanay nechtam as long as you
do קיום שטרות kiyum shtaros you're okay. You're allowed to do a
normal קיום שטרות. kiyum shtaros. This was just a תקנה takkana to
make it easier for you. But if there's two people doing the
קיום שטרות kiyum shtaros that's the point. You can't let one person
do it and have it confused with קיום שטרות. kiyum shtaros.
But you can say forget the whole תקנה takkana we'll just do
a normal קיום שטרות
kiyum shtaros here like that was an earlier משנה. mishna. So you're
saying I guess we're trying to make certain boundaries between תקנת עגונות
takkanat agunot and then right keeping things in order right not letting
things just become a mess. All right,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: פשיטא, Pshita, why do I
need this case? Meaning the first line that if you didn't say
you know בפני נכתב bifanay nechtav it's no good. I mean obviously.
התם אמרי חדא זימנא, Hatam amri chada zimna, maybe you can't say
בפני נכתב bifanay nechtav בפני נחתם. bifanay nechtam. So logically so why
do you have to tell me if you don't do it it's
פסול? pasul? So even before you get to the particulars the answer
is obvious. אי מההיא הוה אמינא צריך ואי לא אמר כשר. Ei
me-hahi hava amina tzarich v'ei lo amar kasher. That said it's just
a תקנה takkana to say it. It didn't tell me what the
consequences were of not saying it. קא משמע לן הך משנה Ka
mashma lan hach mishna that not saying it it's פסול pasul and
this משנה mishna even says it even a slight nuance in how
in saying it incorrectly is פסול. pasul. Okay. And now we're going
to look at that nuance. ובפני נכתב חציו ובפני נחתם כולו פסול.
Uvfanay nechtav chetzyo uvfanay nechtam kulo pasul. Okay. That's the most that's
the first big חידוש. chidush. I saw the whole thing signed but
I only saw half of it being written. But I'm already saying
half was written which already means that I'm making this as distinct
from קיום שטרות kiyum shtaros and nevertheless that's not enough. Now that's
a חידוש chidush in itself. What about the גמרא Gemara earlier remember
that said that all you had to hear was the scratching of
the quill? Right? So here why is that worse? You said you
saw half of it being written. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so
האי חציו, Hai chetzyo, which חציו? chetzyo? אילימא חציו ראשון Ilima chetzyo
rishon that you saw the first half being written ואמר רבי אלעזר
אפילו לא כתב בו אלא שיטה אחת לשמה שוב אינו צריך. V'amar
Rebbi Elazar afilu lo katav bo ela shita achat lishma shuv eno
tzarich. You only have to hear the first line being written correctly
or one line but that's going to be understood to mean the
first line and then you could assume the rest was okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רב אשי חציו אחרון. Ela amar
Rav Ashi chetzyo acharon. Fine, you heard the end of it being
written but not the beginning. So if the beginning was done first
well you could assume it followed suit and the rest was done
properly as well. But if you just came in for the end
you can't really implicitly testify. at the beginning. Okay, so that is
the first big חידוש chidush and to some degree who cares if
it's all about קיום שטרות, kiyum shtaros, but nevertheless, that's the תקנה.
takana. Now, בפני נכתב כולו ובפני נחתם חציה פסול. B'fanai nichtav kulo
u'v'fanai nechtam chetzyo pasul. You can only testify to one signature to
be valid, which is pretty obvious. But now the אמוראים Amoraim are
going to discuss less obvious cases. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, says רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
ואפילו שנים
מעידים על חתימת יד שני פסול. v'afilu shnayim meidim al chasimas yad
sheni pasul. Let's,
the שליח shaliach says I can testify to the first signature and
you go and you get witnesses to validate the second one. So
that should be fine. The שליח's shaliach testimony works for signature one
and two other witnesses work for signature two. He says no, that's
going to be
פסול. pasul. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? או כולו בקיום הגט או כולו
בתקנת חכמים. O kulo b'kiyum ha'get o kulo b'takanas chachamim. Make up
your mind. It'll either all let make to work through קיום kiyum
or make it work through a normal קיום שטרות kiyum shtaros or
through the תקנה takana בפני נכתב. b'fanai nichtav. You can't use this
תקנה takana halfway and קיום kiyum the other halfway. It seems a
little arbitrary. There's no good סברא sevara why not, but like we
like keeping things in their right boxes.
It's like in ברכות, Brachos, right, when they say you can go
by the opinion that you can דאוון davven מנחה... Mincha...
something like this, maybe, right? And we'll see cases on the עמוד
ב amud beis about it's either all A or all B, none
of the nothing middle. They did an interesting thing, a study, where
like they showed people like these different shapes of things, like you
know, like a perfect triangle and then one that's a little rounded
edge or a little bit off, you know, squares and circles and
things like a little bit off. And they asked people to like
you know, identify like what are all the triangles on the page,
what are all the squares on the page. And then the people
that like would include, would like and then they asked people like
what their political views were on certain things, and people that were
prepared to sort of acknowledge a certain amount of variation, like yeah,
that's also that's still a triangle, that's still a triangle, they were
the liberals. And the people that were very rigid, no, that's not
a triangle, it's not exactly straight or whatever, much more tracked with
people's conservative political views.
So strange if you think about it. Anyway, so רב חסדא Rav
Chisda says I don't care if there's not a סברא sevara for
this. You're either in box A or you're in box B.
You can't fit a square peg in a round hole.
There you go. Okay, so that's what רב חסדא Rav Chisda says.
או כולו בקיום הגט או כולו בתקנת חכמים. O kulo b'kiyum ha'get
o kulo b'takanas chachamim. מתקיף לה רבה, Maskif la Rava, and רבה
Rava challenges: מי איכא מידי דאילו אמר חד כשר וכי אמרי תרי
פסול? Mi ika midi d'ilu amar chad kasher v'chi amri srei pasul?
What does that... doesn't make any sense.
If the שליח shaliach had said the second witness was okay, was
validated, we'd be okay. All of a sudden you got two good
כשר kosher witnesses validating it and you're saying it's no good? So
that doesn't make sense. אלא אמר רבה, Ela amar Rava, רבה Rava
said, if you want to make a חידוש chidush here, it would
be this. אפילו
הוא ואחד מעידים על חתימת יד שני פסול. Afilu hu v'echad meidim
al chasimas yad sheni pasul. Now, this also sounds like you could
say just because you add somebody, but here at least there's a
סברא sevara here. רבה Rava says the שליח shaliach says I recognize
witness A, the first signature, and then the שליח shaliach plus ראובן
Reuven say that they validate the second signature. Okay? Now, why should
that be a problem? Okay, now one thing to clarify here also,
which is a debate of רש"י, Rashi, תוספות, Tosafos, I'll just mention,
is in this scenario where the שליח shaliach is saying, the שליח
shaliach says
בפני נחתם b'fanai nechtam ראובן's Reuven signature, and then the שליח shaliach
and another guy are validating שמעון's Shimon signature. Now, is the שליח
shaliach even saying בפני נחתם b'fanai nechtam שמעון's Shimon signature? I wasn't
there to see שמעון Shimon sign it. Okay, but me and somebody
else are saying we recognize שמעון's Shimon signature. Okay, so partly, what
would be if the שליח shaliach instead of saying no other guy,
the שליח shaliach just came and
said I wasn't there for the signing of either ראובן Reuven or
שמעון's Shimon signature, but I recognize both of them. So רש"י Rashi
said that actually would count, you can say that without saying בפני
נחתם. b'fanai nechtam. תוספות Tosafos very strongly disagrees. If you want to
do the the whole idea of the תקנה takana is that we
treat it different than קיום שטרות kiyum shtaros and you have to
testify to directly
witnessed. Fine, but we'll work with תוספות. Tosafos. I agree with you.
But I just wanted to put that out there. So according to
what happened is you switched gears. You're not allowed to say I
recognize the signature. That doesn't work with the תקנה. takana. So for
ראובן Reuven you said I was there for it. That works with
the תקנה. takana. For שמעון Shimon I can't say I was there,
so I can't just testify to שמעון, Shimon, but me and my
pal will come and say we recognize שמעון's Shimon signature. Okay? So
you get it? So for ראובן Reuven you say בפני
נחתם, b'fanai nechtam, and for שמעון Shimon you say...
בפני נחתם,
b'fanai nechtam, excuse me, בפני נחתם, b'fanai nechtam, and for שמעון Shimon
you say my pal and I validate. You say מכירי. makiri. Okay?
מכירי. makiri. Okay? So if you were just one guy, that wouldn't
work, because you have to do בפני נחתם b'fanai nechtam according to
תוספות Tosafos for the signature. But what happens is here you've got
the שליח, shaliach, okay, and
that his בפני נחתם b'fanai nechtam works for ראובן, Reuven, and here
you've got the שליח shaliach plus another guy. Okay, so you can't
say בפני נחתם, bifanay nechtam, so for the, so once he's not
saying בפני נחתם, bifanay nechtam, you need to do it through a
process of validation. You can't do it through the תקנה. takana. Okay,
so that's what's happening. Now you would say, okay, but at least
you got two witnesses here, right? So why should that be not
good? Okay, you could've, maybe, you know, בפני נחתם bifanay nechtam would
work, shouldn't two witnesses make it even better? Okay, but the point
is, so this here, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda said, if any
two guys here would be invalid. You have to choose: either do
the תקנה takana or
do normal קיום שטרות. kiyom shtaros. רבא Rava said, I don't get
it. If you're having two witnesses here, it should be totally okay,
it should just be better. But רבא Rava stays, if one of
those witnesses down here is the שליח, shaliach, okay, and now רבא's
Rava's going to tell you why that actually is not such a
great situation. Let's take a look. So it says like this, it
says, ואחד מן השוק וחתום הוא ואחד מן
השוק פסול—invalid. v'echad min hashuk v'chasum hu v'echad min hashuk pasul מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? But what's the reason? אתי לאחלופי בקיום שטרות
דעלמא—you're Asi l'achlufay b'kiyom shtaros d'alma going to confuse it with normal
validation of a document, וכנפיק נכי רבעא דממונא אפומא דחד
סהדא—and v'kanafik nechi riv'a d'mamona apuma d'chad sahada you will be taking
out all of the money minus a quarter, you'll be taking out
three quarters of the money on the basis of one witness, which
means what? I come, I bring this שטר, shtar,
somebody here, Michael produces this lovely שטר shtar to בית דין, Beis
Din, okay, and it has on it my signature and David's signature,
okay, and I say, so now Michael has to get this שטר
shtar validated. So how does he validate it? He either gets witnesses
that testify they recognize the signature, or he gets the witnesses themselves
that signed that testify to their own signature. So I come to
בית דין Beis Din and I say, yeah, that's my signature. Okay,
now is there anybody here who can validate David's signature because David
isn't around? Okay, so Seth knows David's signature as well, so Seth
and I validate David's signature, okay. So now on this document, it's
become validated, three quarters of the validation came by me, right? One
signature was all by me, that's half, right, my own signature, and
the second signature came through mine and Seth's testimony, that's half of
the second signature, so three quarters of the document has been validated—exists
because of one witness, okay, and that's not the way it's supposed
to work, it's supposed to be that two witnesses equally somehow validate
the document. So therefore that's invalid for קיום שטרות. kiyom shtaros. So
what, so what רבא Rava says is this case looks like it,
okay? You validated signature one—now that wasn't your own signature, it was
somebody else's—but you were able to do it yourself because you were
able to say בפני נחתם, bifanay nechtam, okay, and then here, you
and somebody else validated the second one, so three quarters of the
document has become כשר kosher through your testimony, okay. So because of
that, he basically says that's why it's invalid—וכנפיק נכי רבעא דממונא אפומא
דחד סהדא. v'kanafik nechi riv'a d'mamona apuma d'chad sahada. So מתיב ליה
רב אשי—רב אשי challenges this. מי גמידי דאי מסיק ליה הוא לכוליה
דיבורא כשר—wait Mi gemidi d'ee masik lay hu v'chulei dibura kosher a
minute, he says, that's by a normal שטר, shtar, why by a
normal שטר shtar does that not work? Because in your case of
your normal שטר, shtar, there I could not—I could not validate the
whole שטר. shtar. So if I couldn't validate the whole one, I
couldn't validate three quarters of it either, right, that's the normal שטר,
shtar, right, the case where I just gave. Here, if he was
present for Shimon's signature, he could validate the whole thing! So in
theory, he can validate the whole thing, why can't we let him
validate three quarters of it? Okay. Even better. So מי גמידי דאי
מסיק ליה הוא לכוליה דיבורא—and Mi gemidi d'ee masik lay hu v'chulei
dibura he finishes his words, meaning was he able to say בפני
נחתם bifanay nechtam on the second signature, כשר—השתא דאיכא אחד בהדיה פסול?
pasul,
Now that you're using two people for the second signature and you
have to—you can't say בפני נחתם. bifanay nechtam. But so what? If
it's three quarters by him, we would allow the whole thing to
be by him if he was able to say בפני נחתם. bifanay
nechtam. Now רבא, Rava, who made a similar challenge to רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, he feels it's different. Look, I understand in principle you're
right, this should be okay, but I have a practical reason why
I'm saying it's no good, because somebody will see this and they'll
come to פסקן pasken in a similar way by קיום שטרות. kiyom
shtaros. Okay, in principle there's nothing wrong with this, but his רבא's
Rava's point was
אתי לאחלופי בקיום שטרות—you'll asi l'achlufay b'kiyom shtaros witness this and you'll
say, hey, I was just in בית דין Beis Din and I
saw one guy, you know, validate one signature all by his own
and then do half for the other. So then you might come
and think that that works in general by קיום שטרות, kiyom shtaros,
okay. So in principle this is okay, but it looks too similar
to a case that we say is invalid by קיום שטרות. kiyom
shtaros.
So אלא אמר רב אשי—anyway, Ella amar Rav Ashi so okay—אלא Ella
אמר רב אשי—רב אשי says, I think those two cases are both
totally fine. If you want a case that's no good, here's the
case. איהו ואחד מן השוק וחתום הוא ואחד מן השוק פסול. ihu
v'achad min hashuk v'chasum hu v'achad min hashuk pasul. Let's say according
to רב אשי, Rav Ashi you say
בפני נחתם—ראובן's signature—oh, by
the... and ראובן Reuven signature works because of בפני נחתם. bifanay nechtam
All right. So that's a case where it's all one person, בפני
נחתם. bifnai nechtam. It's all one person, but you're not picking one
mode. You're either, you know, partly you're using the תקנת חכמים takanat
chachamim of בפני נחתם, bifnai nechtam. partly you're using the mode of
קיום שטרות kiyuum shtarot of validating your own signature.
We didn't make it better by switching modes.
But they just think you need a bit of כתיבה. ktiba. Right.
So it says well no he said the כתיבה ktiba also hits
for some reason. אפילו אומר אני הוא עד השני פסול. Afilu omer
ani hu ed hasheni pasul. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? או כולו בקיום
הגט או כולו בתקנת חכמים. O kulo bekiyum haget o kulo betakanat
chachamim. Okay. And now you understand. He's saying like when רב חסדא
Rav Chisda said if you have two witnesses down here it's no
good because it's תקנת חכמים, takanat chachamim, the argument was that's absurd.
We just made it better. We upgraded it to a full קיום.
kiyum. Okay, but here we didn't make it better. We relied the
whole thing on one guy. But partly one guy with this special
תקנה takana בפני נחתם bifnai nechtam, and partly this one guy with
validating his own signature. We didn't make it better by switching modes.
Okay so if he would have said nothing. He said בפני נחתם
בפני נחתם. bifnai nechtam bifnai nechtam. Then we'd be fine. And which
is true, בפני נחתם. bifnai nechtam All right, whatever.
But he held that since he was the signer. Right.
If he's a-
if he's the same.
That's a good question.
That's a good question. If שמעון Shimon is the signatory, then just
say בפני נחתם, bifnai nechtam. which is true. That's an interesting point.
So you could have found I guess this position. You could have
said like well he made it better, you could have just been
like look you know he just you know he can't and it
is true בפני נחתם. bifnai nechtam, I guess the answer would be
so say that you know but don't switch modes. It was one
thing when you switched modes and made it better and you did
real קיום. kiyum. The argument was how is making it better make
it work? But here you switched modes you know by saying that
I'm the signature and that just confuses things. Keep it in the
same box. Okay so now הגמרא hagemara says like this.
Okay.
תנן. Tnan. בפני נחתם כולו בפני נחתם חציו פסול. Bifnai nechtam kulo
bifnai nechtam chetzyo pasul. Half of the sign which is our case.
Only one signature was done in front of me. אידך חציו היכי
דמי? Idach chetzyo heichi dami? What happened with the other signature? אילימא
דליכא דקא מסהיד עליה כלל, Ilima delika deka masheid alei klal, nobody's
testifying to it? השתא אחד אומר בפני נכתב ואחד אומר בפני נחתם
דקא מסהדי אכולה כתיבה,
Hashta echad omer bifnai nichtav ve’echad omer bifnai nechtam deka masahadi
akula ktiba, where if you have a case where somebody says one
witness says it was written one שליח shaliach says it was written
one says it was
signed והאי קא מסהיד אכולה כתיבה והאי קא מסהיד אכולה חתימה, vehai
ka masahid akula ktiba vehai ka masahid akula chatima, one is fully
testifying on the writing, one on the signing, פסול, pasul. it's invalid.
So חציו מבעיא ליה? chetzyo mibaia lei? Of course it's if nobody
validates the second signature. So the גמרא's gemara basically doing like the
point like it's being מדייק medayek in the language of the משנה.
mishna. That it should be obvious by this stage in the משנה
mishna that if you only are testifying to one signature and nothing
about the second signature obviously it's פסול. That's not a חידוש. chiddush.
Like if you're testifying on half of the כתיבה ktiba it's no
good and the כתיבה ktiba doesn't really even matter. Right? And just
testifying on half of the כתיבה's ktiba no good. So certainly if
you're testifying only on half of the signatures it's no good. So
that's like obvious. So if the משנה mishna says it's not good
when you testify on one of the signatures, clearly for there to
be a חידוש chiddush here we must be talking about some other
way that the other signature was validated or there would be no
חידוש, chiddush, it would be too פשוט. pashut. So אלא או כרבה
או כרב אשי. ella o kerava o kerav ashi. If it's-
so it must be telling me that somehow something is done with
the second signature.
What would be- what would be the case? It's either like רבה
Rava said that the guy basically validated it with somebody else from
the שוק. shuk. Or like רב אשי Rav Ashi that he basically
said the second signature was his own. Okay but it must be
some חידוש. chiddush. It must be one of the things we've been
saying.
ולאפוקי מדרב חסדא. Ule’apuki miderav chisda. But to exclude רב חסדא. Rav
Chisda. And the question is what do you mean to exclude רב
חסדא? Rav Chisda? How do you know what it's excluding? You're just
saying it must be something else is going on here right? But
what the basically the point is that רב חסדא Rav Chisda was
a huge חידוש. chiddush. רב חסדא Rav Chisda was I'm doing signature
one, you can have a complete two other strangers validate signature two
and it could still be no good. Okay. That is like a
huge חידוש, chiddush, right? Because like because it's like a complete 100%
acceptable validation of the second signature. Why should it be no good?
So the גמרא's gemara saying is the- if that was the חידוש
chiddush of the משנה, mishna, it would have said it more explicitly.
If the משנה, mishna, it's like a very funny argument. If the
משנה mishna is just implying that something was done to the second
signature and nevertheless it's still invalid, then it must be something relatively
minimal was done with the second signature, not something huge. But if
something huge like רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, it was 100% validated normally,
the משנה mishna would not have just been suggesting that by implication.
It should have said that like much more explicitly. Okay so הגמרא
hagemara says אמר לך רב חסדא, amar lach Rav Chisda, רב חסדא
Rav Chisda would say back to you, ולטעמיך בפני נכתב אבל לא
בפני נחתם למה לי? u’letamecha bifnai nichtav aval lo bifnai nechtam lama
li? You can't say that every line in the משנה mishna is
coming to imply some חידוש. chiddush. Okay. Because if that was true,
when it says בפני נכתב bifnai nichtav and not בפני נחתם, bifnai
nechtam. what's the חידוש chiddush there? I mean obviously it wasn't signed
in front of you it's no good. אלא לא זו אף זו
קתני lo zu af zu katni means not only is A not
good but B is not good. Yeah, when we're listing cases that
are not good even though some of the earlier cases are more
obvious, you know, so fine, so הכא נמי לא זו אף זו
קתני. hacha nami lo zu af zu katni. So when we say
the second signature wasn't validated, it's no good, it's not to infer
from that that there's some... that it's a חידוש chiddush that something
else was being done with the second signature and it's still no
good. The whole point is that the משנה Mishnah is just, you
know, laying out some same scenarios and they're not all big חידושים.
chiddushim. It was a very strange back and forth because the bottom
point is is that normally when you say that the משנה Mishnah
isn't telling you anything, it's because you're denying there's a חידוש. chiddush.
Here רב חסדא Rav Chisda is saying the bigger חידוש chiddush of
everybody. רב חסדא Rav Chisda is saying that even if the second
signature was completely fully validated, it's no good. Okay, but the גמרא's
Gemara's question was, such a big חידוש chiddush it should have said
so explicitly. Since it's not saying that explicitly, it's obviously not making
a חידוש chiddush the size of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. But רב
חסדא's Rav Chisda's point back is, it's not making any חידוש. chiddush.
Some of the cases are just laying out some obvious scenarios. You
don't have to read something into every case of the משנה. Mishnah.
All right. Anyways, be that as it may, bottom line is is
that the משנה Mishnah says if the second signature isn't validated, it's
no good, and and you have a three-way debate of אמוראים Amoraim
about cases where the signature is validated and it's still no good.
Okay, רב חסדא Rav Chisda says even validated by strangers, it's no
good, you have to pick which תקנה takanah you're doing. רבא Rava
says validated by the same guy, it's no good because that looks
like an invalid case of קיום שטרות kiyom shtarot where three-quarters is
being done by one guy. And the last one, who was the
last one? רב אשי Rav Ashi, says that no, it's all just
you the one guy, but you either do everything by... but do
the whole thing by בפני נחתם. bifnai nechtam, You can't do half
by בפני נחתם b'fanay nechtam. and half by talking about your own
signature. Okay, so those are the three חידושים. chiddushim. Now that we've
introduced this idea of either pick A or B, don't do like
a little of each, okay, we're going to use have discuss that
in some analogous cases. Let's just read one for now.
אמר רב חסדא גידוד חמשה ומחיצה חמשה אין מצטרפין. Amar Rav Chisda
gidud chamisha u'mechitza chamisha ein mitztarfin. If you have a, the way
רש"י Rashi reads it, a hole that's five טפחים tfachim deep and
a fence on top of it that's five טפחים tfachim high, they
don't combine to be a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay, so you
got it? So what you basically have is, let's erase our...
hold on, where's my eraser?
So here you've got your...
here's a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, a ten טפח tfach well, okay.
You're down here, okay, that's a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid because you've
got walls ten טפח tfach high. Okay, or you know another רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid is is that you've got fence, right?
Right?
Okay, and it's a very tall
ten טפחים. tfachim. Okay, because you've got walls ten טפחים tfachim high.
Those are your classic רשויות היחיד. reshuyot hayachid. What happens if you've
got a well that's five טפחים, tfachim,
okay, and it's got on it a fence around it that are
another five טפחים. tfachim. Okay, is that a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid
or not? Is that a רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid? So that's what
he said. Do you combine the well and the wall? Okay. Now,
part of the reason this is a חידוש, chiddush, from the outside
perspective,
okay, it's only a five טפח tfach barrier, right? But from the
inside you have ten טפח tfach walls all around you. All right,
so גידוד חמשה ומחיצה חמשה, gidud chamisha u'mechitza chamisha, he says אין
מצטרפין, ein mitztarfin, they don't combine. עד דאיכא או כולו במחיצה או
כולו בגידוד, ad d'ika o kulo b'mechitza o kulo b'gidud, all wall
or all with a with a well, with a ditch. דאמר מרימר,
d'amar Mareimar, but מרימר Mareimar said, no it's not true, גידוד חמשה
ומחיצה חמשה מצטרפין, gidud chamisha u'mechitza chamisha mitztarfin, they do combine. והלכתא
מצטרפין, v'hilchata mitztarfin,
and the הלכה halacha is that they do combine. Okay, so I
just want to say and then we'll go on with other cases
of half of A and half of B tomorrow. That's the scenarios
we're up to. But I do want to say that תוספות Tosafot
says it's obvious that this combines because from the inside you are
sort of ten טפחים tfachim all around, so this is obvious. For
תוספות, Tosafot, the חידוש chiddush was the following. For תוספות, Tosafot, he
gave two other scenarios. One was,
right, that what happens if, when we say גידוד, gidud, I don't
know how you read it with the word גידוד, gidud, but let's
say we're talking about you're on top of a, you're on top
of a mound. If this mound is ten טפחים tfachim high, it
works, okay? So then from the perspective again of the people down
here, they've got a ten טפח tfach barrier, right? But
let's say this mound is five טפחים tfachim high and you've got
a five טפח tfach wall, okay, around you. So then from the
perspective down here, this guy is encountering a five טפח tfach wall,
but from your, a ten טפח tfach wall, but from your... From
your perspective, right, you're only encountering a five טפח *tefach* wall. It's
like, it's like it's reverse. The תוספות *Tosfos* says this case תוספות
*Tosfos* says is obvious. This case תוספות *Tosfos* says is less obvious.
תוספות *Tosfos* says this is the case that we're talking about, not
this one. Okay, anyway, either way we פוסקן *pasken* that they combine.
Alright, so we will pick up with these types of cases tomorrow.
A nice little break of the fun from
the fun. So the משנה Mishnah says as follows: קונם שאני טועם,
Konam she'ani to'em, if a person says Konam that I taste, it
means he is forbidden from tasting. We explained this because he is
saying may what I taste be forbidden like a קרבן. korban. But
then the משנה Mishnah says something very interesting: if he says, קונם
שאני לא טועם, Konam she'ani lo to'em, Konam that I do not
taste, the משנה says it is forbidden. It still means he is
not allowed to taste. This is very difficult, because שאני לא טועם
she'ani lo to'em should mean if I do not taste. It should
be a vow to taste. But the גמרא Gemara says no, we
follow לשון בני אדם, lashon bnei adam, the way people speak. And
people often add an extra לא. lo. They say I am not
going or I am going and they throw in a לא. lo.
It is like a person saying I won't not do it. They
just mean I won't do it. So here too, the לא lo
is extra. It is what we call a לאו יתירא, lav yaseira,
an extra no. Therefore, both cases mean the same thing: he is
forbidden from tasting. Now, why is נדרים Nedarim different than שבועות? Shavuos?
In שבועות, Shavuos, the rules are very strict. If you say שבועה
שאוכל, Shavuah she'ochal, you must eat. If you say שבועה שלא אוכל,
Shavuah she'lo o'chal, you must not eat. But נדרים Nedarim is different
because נדרים Nedarim goes after the way people talk, לשון בני אדם.
lashon bnei adam. Since people talk this way, adding an extra לא,
lo, the
vow
is
valid
as
a
prohibition
against
tasting.